<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Most straunge and wounderfull accident happened at Weersburch by Franckford, by a most fearefull earthquake and daknesse [sic], with a mighty tempest of thunder and lightning also a most dreadfull embassage vttered to the governour of that Cittie, by three straunge children which were found in a wood, threatning destruction to that countrie, and to all christendome /</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14913</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25219.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2965</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">29605758</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 29605758</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28024</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14913)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28024)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1860:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Most straunge and wounderfull accident happened at Weersburch by Franckford, by a most fearefull earthquake and daknesse [sic], with a mighty tempest of thunder and lightning also a most dreadfull embassage vttered to the governour of that Cittie, by three straunge children which were found in a wood, threatning destruction to that countrie, and to all christendome /</title>
                  <author>T. C.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 10 p., [2] leaves of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Barley, and are to bee sold at his shop in Gracious streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Illustration consists of two copies of the same  plate.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Disasters --  Germany --  Religious aspects.</term>
               <term>Omens.</term>
               <term>Earthquakes --  Germany.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:28024:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28024:1"/>
            <p>A moſt ſtraunge and wounderfull accident, happened at <hi>Weersburch by Franckford, by a moſt</hi> fearefull Earthquake and dakneſſe, with a mightie tempeſt of Thunder and Lightning.</p>
            <p>Alſo a moſt dreadfull Embaſſage, vttered to the Gouernour of that Cittie, by three <hi>ſtraunge Children which were found in a Wood,</hi> threatning deſtruction to that Countrie, and to all Chriſtendome.</p>
            <p>Firſt it was publiſhed in Print at <hi>Franckford,</hi> next at <hi>Cullen</hi>vpon <hi>Rhyne,</hi> and laſt at <hi>Nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weghen.</hi> And now Tranſlated out of Duch in to Engliſh, by <hi>T. C.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by William Barley, and are to bee ſold at his ſhop in Gracious ſtreete. 1600.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:28024:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:28024:2"/>
            <head>A moſt ſtraunge and wonderfull acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, happened at <hi>Weersburch,</hi> by <hi>Franckford,</hi> by a moſt fearefull Earthquake and darkneſſe, with a mightie tempeſt of Thunder and lightning. And of a dreadfull Embaſſage, vttered to the Gouernour of that Cittie: by three ſtraunge Children, which were found in a wood, threatning deſtruction to that Countrie, and to all Chriſtendome.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight iuſt is the Lord in all his iudgments, but yet moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful to ſuch as doe repent, and turne away from their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes: and althogh oft times hee bee ſeuere in his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yet dooth hee long for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare before hee execute his wrath, giuing many war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings to all finners to repent and leaue off their wicked liuing: and dealing with vs euen as a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing Father doth with his children, firſt threatning vs for our faultes, and in hope of amendment, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing and ſuffering vs, to ſee if we wil take war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and leaue off our euill doings. But when hee ſeeth that by no meanes we will be wonne to dread his iudgements, then he taketh his rod of affliction
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:28024:3"/>in hand, and therewith <gap reason="illegible" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>urgeth the obſtinate and rebellious: For although the Pſalmiſt ſaith in one place, <hi>That he is verie mercifull, ſlow to anger, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundant in goodnes:</hi> It in an other places he ſaith. <hi>The Lord is righteous and iuſt, and rewardeth all men according to their deeds:</hi> So that his mercie and iuſtice are of equall quantitie, and as hee ſheweth mercy to the humble and contrite, ſo hee executeth his iudgement vppon the froward and vngodly. And yet notwithſtanding, although we ſee &amp; heare dayly what tokens hee ſendeth vs, as fauourable warnings, and what iudgements hee executeth as terrible threatnings: yet wee ſtill goe on careleſſely in our former wickedneſſe, making no more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of all his admonitions, then of a matter no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing appertinent vnto vs.</p>
            <p>It is not longe ſince hee afflicted vs heere in England. Firſt, with peſtilence and mortalitie, and now laſt by death and famaine, and euen ſo long as our puniſhment continued, ſo long wee in ſome ſort ſought vnto him, but now it hath pleaſed him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to ſend vs our former health and plentie, wee in greater aboundance, daily commit more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous ſinnes then before, and by how much more the mercie of God is ſhewed vnto vs, ſo much the more doe we continually tranſgreſſe, neglecting his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and giuing our ſelues to all ſinfull luſtes and voluptuous pleaſures, taking pleaſure and delight in all the moſt deteſtable and abhominable ſinnes that are in the world. Young men and women, in pride and whoredome, and old folkes, in couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and gluttonie: But wherefore doe I impute
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:28024:3"/>part to young and part to old? For ſurely although thoſe ſinnes bee moſt rife in theſe eſtates, yet both young and old are partakers in them all, and in a great many more, ſo as I may ſay that both young and old, great and ſmall, of all ages, and of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions: are apt to all manner of deadly ſinnes and pernicious vices. And although we haue the glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, plentifully preached amongſt vs, and many thouſands of good, faithful, and painefull Paſtours and Miniſters, to diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute the ſame amongſt vs. Yet there is none of any other Heathen nations, and erronious Religion that are ſo ſlacke, in their deuotion as we are, nor ſo negligent and careleſſe in the worſhip and honor of their falſe Idols and fained Gods, as we are in dutie and reuerence vnto our true God and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly father. This is a grieuous caſe, and of all things moſt lamentable, that we being by profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſtians, and bearing the name of Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to ſo worthie a Captaine as our Sauiour is, ſhould make ſo ſmal reſiſtance againſt our enemies the world, the fleſhe and the diuell, as to let them harbour and remaine amongſt vs, executing their malice vpon our wretched ſoules as they doe. Is it not great ſhame for vs being of ſo excellent a profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, to take ſo little regard and care thereof, and to ſee them of falſe and famed, damned, and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious opinions, ſo careful in maintaining their moſt wicked hereſies? Yes ſurely it is great ſhame, and greatly to bee feared, that thoſe ignorant Heathen nations, ſhal in the day of iudgment riſe vp againſt vs, and condemne vs for the ſmall care and regard that we take of the truth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:28024:4"/>
And ſurely I would wiſh euerie Chriſtian ſoule to take heede: and haue more regard of the honour of God then before times hee hath had, leaſt hee in his iuſt iudgements, bring vtter ruine and deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vpon vs all, as hee hath lately threatned, by theſe tokens which now I purpoſe to declare, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſing thee whoſoeuer thou bee, that either readeſt or heareſt the ſame, not to eſteeme lightly of the matter, but to alter thy mind and leaue off thy wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe in time, while the Lord will bee found to ſhew mercie vnto thee. And ſo briefely to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
            <p>Vpon the twentie day of Iuly laſt paſt, <hi>1600.</hi> A moſt fearefull iudgement of God, happened in the Cittie of <hi>Weersburch</hi> by <hi>Franckford,</hi> where al at one time the Lord ſent a mightie Earthquake, and darkneſſe, with a great and fearefull tempeſt of Thunder and Lightning, which continued for the ſpace of fiue whole howers in moſt dreadfull man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſo that all the inhabitants of the Citie, thought ſurely the laſt iudgement day then to haue beene come, the terrible ſhaking of the earth, cauſed the people both ſmall and great to forſake their houſes, (and finding no place for ſuccor wherein they durſt abide) did runne vp and down the ſtreets, weeping and crying in moſt dolefull manner. Many Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and ſtonewalles, with other buildings, fell dawne by reaſon of extreame ſhaking of the earth, and in their fall, killed and maimed a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Chriſtian people, the ſuddainneſſe of this fearefull tempeſt, put the poore inhabitants in ſuch extreame feare, as no man had any minde of any thing in his houſe, no, the huſband neuer remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:28024:4"/>his wife, nor the wife her huſband, but were ſo exceedingly aſtoniſhed, that they ran vp &amp; downe the ſtreetes from place to place, like mad or fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticke perſons.</p>
            <p>The Thunder and lightning, was likewiſe ſo terrible, as the lightning ceazing vpon the houſes, burned an hundred and twentie of them downe to the ground: and by reaſon of the peoples feare, there was no man that vſed any kind of meanes to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the force of the fire.</p>
            <p>The man that had now beene ther, to haue ſeene the demeanour of theſe poore fearefull ſoules, and could without feare and aſtoniſhment, haue noted their behauiour: might there haue ſeene a moſt liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Map of miſerie and miſfortune.</p>
            <p>During the time of this tempeſt, another moſt ſtraunge and dreadfull accident happened in the Cittie. For a man of a moſt ſtraunge complection, appeared to many people: his hayre on his head ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be flames of burning fier, his eyes ſtood ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in moſt fearefull and gaſtly maner: his beard all growne out of order, that by viſage hee ſeemed like a wild man, in his right hand he held a bloudie ſword, and in his left hand a rod, from whoſe bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches bloud dropped in aboundance, his looke was ſterne and reuengfull, and his words ful of terrour, which were theſe.</p>
            <p>Thus ſaith the Lord, your ſinnes haue mooued me to wrath, and your tranſgreſſions haue prouo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked my diſpleaſure, therefore except you ſpeedily repent and leaue off your wickedneſſe, I wil vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:28024:5"/>deſtroy you from the face of the earth, and behold this bloudie Sword, that I hold in my right hand, betokeneth dreadfull warre, which the Lord will bring vppon you ſpeedily, except vnfained repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. The rod that I haue in my left hand, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the puniſhment which the Lord wil inflict vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you, becauſe you will not bee warned, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake your pride, and ſuch other abhominable ſinnes, for as hee hath longe forborne you, ſtill admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing and exhorting you by his Preachers, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme your ſelues and amend your liues: So now ſeeing no other meanes will ſerue, hee purpoſeth to take his rod of affliction in hand, and to correct your ſinnes moſt ſeuerely. And ſeeing mercie will not preuaile, nor you make no account thereof, hee will now execute his iudgementes vppon you. And ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vttered theſe and ſuch like ſpeeches, hee vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed away: at whoſe departure there was heard ſuch a ſorrowfull howling and crying: that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple more affraid of this wounder then of all the tempeſt before, were now with feare ſo mightily aſtoniſhed, as they rather ſeemed dead men then li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing creatures.</p>
            <p>Not long after, it pleaſed God that the tempeſt ceaſed, and the weather brake vp. which comforted the Citizens hearts, but yet this ioy was not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect with the moſt part, for there you might ſee ſome wayling for the loſſe of their goods and houſes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed with fire, others making woefull lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for their huſbands and children, ſearching a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the dead bodies which were burnt and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:28024:5"/>ſlaine, with the fire and fall of the buildings, heere one crying and wayling of his wounds, gotten in the time of the tempeſt, there another ſorrowing for the loſſe of his friends, in ſuch pittifull manner, as would haue mooued the moſt ſtonie hard, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>durate heart to relent, and take compaſſion: but al in vaine were theſe lamentations, for that by them no man is able to recouer ſuch loſſes, wherfore eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie one as well as they could, ſtriuing to comfort themſelues, made this their chiefeſt ioy, that it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God to ſtay the tempeſt, and in ſome meaſure to appeaſe his wrath.</p>
            <p>Some two or three daies after: to ſhew foorth the great ioye that they receiued by the mercye of God, in ſparing them at that time. The Gouernour of the Cittie with ſome other of his friends, tooke Waggon, entending for their recreation, to ride to the next Cittie called <hi>Ausburch,</hi> being not farre diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant from thence, and as they were in the mid way in a certaine Wood called <hi>Rade,</hi> where ſuddainely they heard a great noyſe and crie of certaine chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and looking about could ſee nothing: vppon that the Gouernour ſent the Waggoner to ſee if he could find the perſons, from whome that clamour proceeded, who went and ſought all about, but could find no bodie, ſo when he had ſought a great while in vaine, at laſt he returned againe to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernour, telling him that hee had ſought in euerie place neere thereabouts, but could neither ſee nor heare any ſuch matter. This aunſwere made them greatly to wonder, for ſtill they heard the crie low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:28024:6"/>then before: which encreaſed their deſire ſo much, as the Gouernour bad the Waggoner to driue forwards into the Wood, to ſee if they could by any meanes know the reaſon of this clamour: Not long had they ridden before they came to a croſſe way, where fower waies met, where they ſpied three children, two boyes and one gerle. The Gerle had vpon her head a coſtly Call, made of the neweſt and ſtatelieſt faſhion, that is at this preſent worne, vpon her lower-parts a paire of Breeches, like a man of the neweſt faſhion likwiſe, both which attires, ſignified pride, the one in women, the other in men. The Girle approaching neere vnto the Waggon, ſpake to the Gouernour as followeth.</p>
            <p>The extreame pride that raigneth in theſe daies among Chriſtians, hath ſo much prouoked the Lords diſpleaſure, that it hath cauſed him to ſend vs downe from heauen, to pronounce his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt you all, and to tell you that hee hath promiſed vtterly to roote you out and deſtroy you, except you ſpeedily repent, and regard the fauour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and mercifull warnings that hee ſendeth you by vs: So hauing vttered ſuch like ſpeeches, ſhee likewiſe vaniſhed away in a great flaſh of Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and was ſeene no more.</p>
            <p>The next approached one of the Boyes, who was clad in <hi>Turkes</hi> apparel, who threatned dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full warre againſt all Chriſtendome, and that the <hi>Turke</hi> ſhould according to an auncient Prophecie: come and ouer-runne that Land, and bring his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie into the Cittie of <hi>Culen</hi> vppon <hi>Rhyne,</hi> which is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:28024:6"/>the place from whence the Reniſh wine commeth: and with ſword and fire ſhould deſtroy all thoſe places in which he entered, and this hee ſaid ſhould fall out the next yeare without faile, except ſpeedie repentance. And that their land ſhould be brought to ſuch extremitie through the want of men, that there ſhould not be left in all the Countrie a man to follow the plough, ſo as all the countrie ſhould bee deſolate and vnfruitfull.</p>
            <p>Then came the other Boye, who holdeth in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his hands, a peece of their Countrie money called a Reall, and hee ſaid that in certaine time af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the <hi>Turke</hi> ſhould bee beaten backe againe into <hi>Hungarie,</hi> and then ſhould bee ſuch plentie, as no man ſhould haue need to borrow of his neighbour, but they ſhould haue Gold and Siluer at will: but there ſhould follow ſuch peſtilence &amp; contagion, as the number of the people ſhould be ſo much demini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, that victuals ſhall bee ſo plentie, as for three Stiuers (which is in Engliſh money ſome ſeuen pence halfe penie) a man ſhould buy a buſhell of of Wheate, and for halfe ſo much a buſhell of Rie. But a dead mans Coffin ſhould not bee found, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a man would giue for the ſame a Duck at of Gold, ſo grieuous the plague ſhould be.</p>
            <p>When all theſe ſpeeches were vttered, they made the Gouernour ſweare, to publiſh the effect of their words in all their Dominions, and to all other nations neere adioyning vnto them, which they tooke their oathes to performe. And ſo they made letters of Credence, ſealed with their Seales
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:28024:7"/>and ſent them from Cittie to Cittie. Firſt to the <hi>Palſgraue,</hi> then from him to the Duke of <hi>Bronſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wicke,</hi> and ſo ouer all the land. This Coppie came into England the twelfth day of this preſent Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of Nouember. <hi>1600.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>The names of thoſe Officers to whome this Embaſſage was vttered. <hi>Iaſper Vromen,</hi> Gouernour of <hi>Weersburch,</hi> which in their language they call the <hi>Scoute,</hi> and <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobus Vos,</hi> Burgomaſter.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FJNIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:28024:7"/>
            <p>
               <figure/>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:28024:8"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:28024:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
